Timothy Horsfield Papers 1684-1771 Mss.974.8.H78
American Philosophical Society
Timothy Horsfield Papers
1684, 1733-1771
Mss.974.8.H78
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet 205 items
An early settler and prominent citizen in the Moravian heartland near Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, Timothy Horsfield was named justice of the peace when Northampton County was formed out of Bucks in 1752, and was one of those given responsibility for the defence of the local white and Christian Indian populations during the French and Indian War. The Horsfield Papers offer a window onto the tumultuous history of northeastern Pennsylvania during the 1750s and 1760s. Comprised largely of correspondence and related documents between Horsfield, William Parsons, and provincial and military authorities, the collection includes important information on the Indian assaults on the region in 1756 and 1757 and the military and diplomatic response.
Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
Early American History Note
Timothy Horsfield was a prominent official in Northampton County in Pennsylvania during the Seven Years' War and its aftermath. This relatively small collection contains a wealth of information on the war. The letters are content rich and often relay details on society and life in the area. MOLE contains a detailed inventory of the letters.
Other Finding Aids note
The Horsfield letters pertaining to Indian affairs are indexed in the online Daythal Kendal Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Related Archival Materials note
The Historical Society of Pennsylvania houses several Horsfield items, including the Timothy Horsfield Letterbook, 1754-1755 (Collection 296) and the Horsfield Receipt book, 1756 (Collection 297), and there are several letters of his in the Northampton County Papers (Collection 456). The papers of William Parsons (Collection 470) also contain valuable contextual material.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donor, Joseph Horsfield of Bethlehem, through John G. E. Heckewelder, 1819.
Scope and Contents note
The Timothy Horsfield Papers offer a window onto the tumultuous history of northeastern Pennsylvania during the 1750s and 1760s. Centered in the region around Bethlehem, Pa., where Horsfield was justice of the peace, the collection is comprised largely of correspondence and related documents between Horsfield, William Parsons, and provincial and military authorities. The collection spans the period from 1684 to 1771, with the bulk from the late 1740s to the early 1760s. It includes particularly important and vivid information on the Indian assaults on the region in 1756 and 1757, and the military and diplomatic response. A typed table of contents is included in the box.
The Horsfield letters were originally laid into two volumes, which were disbound in 1984. The original numeration of the pages has been retained, however the letters have been rearranged in chronological and alphabetical order. Many of the papers bear marginal notations by John G. E. Heckewelder, through whose offices the papers were deposited with the Society.
Some of the earlier material relates to plans to survey land in Pennsylvania, including the “Plantable quantity of Land within the new Purchase” (11 September 1749). One interesting letter by the Count of Hohenlohe to the Governor requests that the Governor of Pennsylvania examine whether the father of a German immigrant from Hohenlohe had been cheated out of his rightful inheritance by a “newlander” (20 May 1752).
The majority of the letters in the Horsfield Papers were written during the critical months of October 1755 through August 1756, when northeastern Pennsylvania was embroiled in violence. There are several depositions and letters that describe the attacks on the community of Brethren at Gnadenhütten. There is also another, somewhat smaller clutch during the summer and fall of 1763 and scattered letters at other times. Concerned with local defense, the raising of militia, intelligence on Indian movements, and forging contacts with Indian allies, the network of Horsfield's correspondents included some of the most prominent figures in provincial Indian affairs, including Benjamin Franklin, Richard Peters, Conrad Weiser, governors Robert Hunter Morris, William Denny, and James Hamilton, and Moravian men of influence such as August Gottlieb Spangeberg and David Zeisberger. An equally prominent assemblage of Native Americans appears in the collection, including Delaware chief Teedyuscung, Lewis Montour, Kolapeeha, and the Mohawk Sachem, Jonathan.
The supremely violent events of the late fall 1755 are particularly well documented, including letters and several depositions relating to the Indian attacks at Penns Creek in October and Gnadenhutten in late November. The latter event underscores a running theme in the collection: the complex web of relations between Christianized (Moravian) Indians, the Moravian brethren, English settlers, and non-Christian Indians.
Biographical/Historical note
Timothy Horsfield (1708-1773) was a butcher and prominent citizen of the Moravian town of Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. He was appointed Justice of the Peace by Governor James Hamilton (1710-1783, APS 1768), when Northampton County was founded in 1752. At the outbreak of the French and Indian War, Horsfield was one of the citizens given responsibility for raising a local militia, mustering supplies, providing intelligence for the military authorities and caring for refugees. In July 1763 he was commissioned a colonel of the militia forces, a position he soon resigned.
Horsfield was born in 1708 in Liverpool, England, and was educated in the parish school. In 1725 he emigrated to Long Island, New York, where his brother Isaac taught him the butcher’s trade. He married Mary Doughty, daughter of a prominent Long Island butcher, in 1731, and in 1734 he became a freeholder. In 1735 Horsfield and his brother leased two stands in the Old Slip Market at the corner of Pearl Street and Old Slip in New York City.
In 1739 Horsfield, who was a member of the Church of England, attended a religious revival meeting of the Methodist evangelist George Whitefield, an event that impressed him. Subsequently, Horsfield became acquainted with the Moravian missionaries Peter Bohler and David Nitchmann, and later regularly opened his home near Brooklyn Ferry to other Moravian missionaries, who were traveling between Europe and the West Indies.
In 1748 Horsfield applied to the Bethlehem authorities to become a resident of the Moravian town. Although permission for him to settle there was not granted until the following year, he did place his children in the town’s Moravian schools in 1748. After Horsfield and his family took up residence in the Oerter house on Market Street they reserved two rooms for visitors to the the town.
Horsfield was the owner of two slaves when the family moved to Bethlehem from New York. His slave Joshua, better known as “Horsfield’s Tony,” was originally from Ibo in Africa, where he had been captured and sold into slavery at the age of 14. In 1750 Joshua was baptized by the Moravian bishop Cammerhoff, and sent to the Moravian colony of Christian’s Spring near Nazareth, Pennsylvania. There, as a result of the experience he gained working for Horsfield, Joshua secured employment as a butcher. Horsfield’s other slave, named Cornelia, was born in Red Hook, New York, in 1728 and died in Bethlehem in 1757.
In 1752 when Northampton County was created out of Bucks County, Governor Hamilton appointed Horsfield Justice of the Peace. His commission began on June 9, 1752, several years prior to the eruption of conflict between the Delaware Indians and British settlers on the Pennsylvania frontier. The influx of European settlers into the Pennsylvania hinterland and the concomitant dispossession of the Indians by legal and extralegal means (such as the notorious Walking Purchase of 1737) had fueled resentments that resulted in Indian raids against their white neighbors. Subsequently, the intertribal rivalry between the Iroquois and the Delaware, and the rivalry between the English and French, provided tinder for the French and Indian War that erupted in 1754. As a public official and a prominent citizen, Horsfield was one of those given responsibility for shoring up local defenses, raising a militia, providing intelligence to military authorities and caring for refugees. He was commissioned a colonel in the militia in 1763, an appointment that caused considerable jealousy. The resentment not only led to his resignation but also cost him his position as Justice of the Peace.
Horsfield died in Bethlehem in 1773. His wife Mary died later that year. The couple had eight children. They included Joseph, born in 1750, a delegate to the Pennsylvania Convention to ratify the Federal Constitution of 1787.
Croghan, George, d.1782; Denny, William; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Hamilton, James, 1710-1783; Longshore, Robert; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764; Parsons, William, 1701-1757; Peters, Richard, 1704-1776; Read, James, 1718-1793; Reed, James; Scull, Nicholas, 1686?-1761?; Shippen, Edward, ca. 1703-1781; Spangenberg, August Gottlieb, 1704-1792; Teedyuscung, ca. 1700-1763; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760; Zeisberger, David, 1721-1808; Colonial Politics; Delaware Indians; Diplomatic History; Diplomatic Material; General Correspondence; Government Affairs; Indians of North America--Pennsylvania--Government relations--To 1789; Iroquois Indians; Maps; Miami Indians; Military History; Military Records; Moravian Indians; Moravians--Pennsylvania--History; Native America; Official Government Documents and Records; Pennsylvania History; Pennsylvania--History--Colonial period, ca.1600-1775; Political Correspondence; Seven Years' War; United States--History--French and Indian War, 1755-1763
- Timothy Horsfield Papers, 1684-1771; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - The draught of the observation made of the river, March 26, 1684; 5; 1 map, 38.6 x 31.7 cm; Longshore, Robert
    Scope and Contents note
    Survey map plotting position of John Long House on New Jersey side of Delaware River relative to Philadelphia.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 21 (1).
  - State of the case of C. Brockden in behalf of his Principal, the Master of the Rolls, 1717; 523; 2p.; Brockden, C.
  - An Exact Account of Lord Fairfax's title to lands in [the Northern Neck of] Virginia, Nov. 29, 1733; 1; 3p.; Paris, Mr.
    and of the printed map now sent which was made up by his commissioners, Description together with some acc't of another map made up at the same time by the king's comm. but wch being a manuscript cannot yet (if ever) be sent from hence...3p. Q. Manuscript.
  - Names of the Chiefs of the Indian's present at the Treaty held at Philadelphia, July 1742; 9; 3p.
    Includes notes on other tribes with which the Six Nations are in alliance.
  - Richard Peters to William Parsons, Sept. 11, 1749; 13; 1p.; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828
    Directing him to survey the land between the Susquehanna and west branch of the Schuylkill, to fulfil the grant of ten percent on all plantation lands to the Proprietaries
  - Warrant of the Surveyor-General to survey ten percent of all vacant land in the Province, Oct. 4, 1749; 11; 1p.; Scull, Nicholas, 1686?-1761?
  - Count Hohenlohe to James Hamilton, May 20, 1752; 19; 1p.; Hohenlohe, Count
    Dated Langenbourg, 1p. F. Manuscript. Respecting the effects of the late George Michael Weismüller, a blacksmith. Translation of a letter to the governor of Pennsylvania.
  - Robrt Levers to William Parsons, Sept. 20, 1753; 23; 1p.; Levers, Robert
    Dated Philadelphia, mentions that about 60 heads of the Twightwees are on their way to see the governor, 1p. 0. Manuscript. Freeman Guide 2219.
  - Summons to convene the Pennsylvania Assembly on August 6th, July 20, 1754; 25; 1p.; Hamilton, James, 1710-1783
    Dated 1p. Manuscript. Contains seal. Command to Nicholas Scull to summon the representative for the county of Northampton to a meeting of the Assembly on August 6th.
  - James Read to Mr. Gordon [William Parsons?], March 12, 1755; 27; 2p.; Reed, James
    Dated Reading. Expressing anxiety for letters; stating the active preparations of the New Englanders for some secret expedition, and that a report was in circulation of the King's intention to draw the French from the Ohio. 2p. F. Manuscript. Mentions B.F. as chief cabinet councilor in Boston. (This letter might be addressed to a Mr. Gordon).
  - Conrad Weiser to William Parsons, Oct(?) 28, 1755; 69; 2p.; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760
    Dated Heidelberg, relating an Indian attack and asking advice. 2p. F. Manuscript. Freeman Guide 2867.
  - to unidentified recipient, Oct. 29, 1755; 31; 1p.; Shippen, Edward
    Dated Lancaster, relative to sending lead and shot and stating that meeting were being held for defence and that a report was current that a body of French and Indians was seen near Carlisle. 1p. O. Manuscript. Freeman Guide 1381.
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Oct. 31, 1755; 33; 1p.; Potts, John
    Potts, James Read, Conrad Weiser and others to the governor of Pennsylvania dated stating their distress and threatening to quarter themselves on inhabitants of Philadelphia if not supported. 1p. F. Manuscript. Copy.
  - to William Parsons, Nov. 1, 1755; 35; 1p.; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760
    Dated Heidleberg, the first. Wishes to see him (written under much anxiety). 1p. F. Manuscript.
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Nov. 2, 1755; 37; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Dated Bethlehem, enclosing an examination of two of the United Brethren on their return from preaching (no.39), respecting an attack made by the French Mohawk Indians near the Susquehanna on 20th Oct. 4p. O. and F. Manuscript. Copy. Freeman Guide 2264.
  - Deposition of Christian Seidle and David Zeisberger, Nov. 10, 1755; 39; 3p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Examination on their return from preaching, respecting, an attack made by the French Mohawk Indians near the Susquehanna on 20th October.
  - to Robert Hunter Morris enclosing, deposition of Phillip Wesa and Godfrey Resler, Nov. 10-15, 1755; 43; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Respecting outrage of Oct. 26th
  - Deposition, Nov. 10-15, 1755; 45; 3p.; Wesa, Phillip
    Enclosed in letter no. 43, respecting outrage of Oct. 26th
  - Deposition, Nov. 15, 1755; 51; 4p.; Schmick, John and Henry Fry
    Enclosed in no. 43, respecting outrage of Oct. 26th
  - to Peter Trexler, Nov. 17, 1755; 59; 2p.; Levan, Jacob
    In German, respecting the Indian murders.
  - Deposition, Nov. 22, 1755; 61; 1p.; Zeisberger, David, 1721-1808
    Relating to Oct. 26 attack.
  - to Joseph Powell, Nov. 23, 1755; 63; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Respecting a convoy for the Indians to Philadelphia.
  - Address to the inhabitants of Northhampton County, Nov. 24, 1755; 65; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Nov. 26, 1755; 55; 3p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Detailing the particulars of the outrage of Oct. 26, with list of those killed.
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Nov. 27, 1755; 67; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Detailing the sufferings of the Brethren and requesting advice.
  - to William Parsons, Nov. 29, 1755; 73; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Acknowledging letters; expressing concern at the outrages of the Indians; hopes for the adoption of measures of defense; thanks for intelligence, etc.
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Nov. 29, 1755; 75; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
  - Account of a murder at Mahony, with the names of the murdered, Nov. 1755; 521; 2p.
  - Address to the Indians lately residing at Gnadenhütten -- now at Bethlehem, to the Governor of the province, Nov. 1755; 531; 2p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Dec. 1, 1755; 77; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Acknowledging preceding; encloses address of the Indians, and stating the dispatch of 12 wagons of grain for the Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Dec. 4, 1755; 79; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Re: building a fort at Gnadenhütten
  - To the Indians lately residing at Gnadenhütten and now at Bethlehem, Dec. 4, 1755; 81; 2p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Address promising protection and expressing commiseration for their losses
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Dec. 4, 1755; 85; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Copy of some data at p.79
  - to William Parsons, Dec. 5, 1755; 87; 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    £60,000 has been granted for defense of the Province and a militia act passed; advising of the despatch of arms and ammunition
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, Dec. 8, 1755; 423; 2p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
  - to William Parsons, Dec. 10, 1755; 49; 1p.; Hays, William
    Re: 6 guns sent by mistake to Easton
  - to William Parsons, Dec. 14, 1755; 80; 3p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Detailing his perplexity and soliciting advice regarding the terrified back inhabitants
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Dec. 14, 1755; 93; 2p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Expressing regret at the outrages of the Indians, and a hope that he would continue to act for the public
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Dec. 14, 1755; 347; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Hoping he will continue to act for public safety, etc.
  - to William Parsons, Dec. 15, 1755; 95; 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Advising of assistance and enclosing £20 for relief of fugitives
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Dec. 17, 1755; 97; 1p.; Spangenberg, August Gottlieb, 1704-1792
    Requesting men, previous to an attack by the Indians on Nazareth
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Jan. 16, 1756; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Recommends Mrs. McClean as an object of charity (see Horsfield papers, v.1, p.127-128).
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Jan. 16, 1756; 127; 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Introducing Mr. McClear as entitled to relief
  - to William Parsons, Jan. 25, 1756; 99; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Forwarding an extract from Benjamin Franklin's letter relative to detachments
  - to Timothy Horsfield, Jan. 28, 1756; 101; 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Arrival of wagons
  - to William Parsons, Feb. 13, 1756; 103; 4p.; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760
    Indian intelligence; death of son-in-law
  - Rough sketch of [illeg] of the Brethren remonstrating against placing more Indians at Bethlehem bringing on by Capt. New Caste, ca. April 1756; 539; 3p.
  - to Timothy Horsfield, March 1, 1756; 105; 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Directing disbursements
  - to William Parsons, March 8, 1756; 107; 1p.; Martin, James
    Burning of his barn by the Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, March 9, 1756; 109; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Alluding to burning of James Martin's, and stating that assistance was sent
  - to Timothy Horsfield, March 11, 1756; 111; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
  - to William Parsons, May 6, 1756; 113; 1p.; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760
    Enclosing Indian treaty
  - Report of his embassy to the hostile Indians on the Susquehanna, June 1, 1756; 115; 6p.; Newcastle, Capt.
  - to William Parsons, June 10, 1756; 123; 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Advising of his return from Virginia and desiring to know present state of country
  - Copy of a letter to Timothy Horsfield and Edmonds, June 15, 1756; 125; 1p.; Unidentified
    concerning the scalping party at Paulinskill and the five Indians now at Bethlehem on their way [to] Tiohogou
  - to Benjamin Franklin, June 19, 1756; 129; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Respecting a review of Forts
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 21, 1756; 133; 1p.; Franklin, William
    Respecting exchange of arms
  - to Robert Hunter Morris, June 21, 1756; 131; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Respecting the Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 22, 1756; 135; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Acknowledging preceding (no. 133) and directing instructions to Capt. Newcastle
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 22, 1756; 333; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Requesting Brethren receive and maintain friendship of Indians at Bethlehem
  - to William Parsons, June 28, 1756; 137; 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Acknowledging letter of the 19th; arrival of British regiments and doubts of their movements
  - Memorandum of what Capt. Newcastle gave us, June 28, 1756; 141; 1p.
  - Instructions to the Brethren respecting friendly Indians, June 28, 1756; 143; 1p.; Newcastle, Capt.
  - Memorandum of an acct. the Indian Nicodemus, June 30, 1756; 145; 2p.
    Memo re: unfriendly Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 30, 1756; 147; 1p.; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828
    Introducing Lieut. Johannes Schlösser and requesting for him all assistance and advice
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 30, 1756; 149; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Acknowledging receipt of Capt. Newcastle's directons
  - to Timothy Horsfield, June 30, 1756; 151; 1p.; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828
    Copy of letter of introduction for Lieut. Johannes Schlösser
  - to Augustus Gottlieb Spangenberg, July 11, 1756; 155; 1p.; Newcastle, Capt.
    Re: Pockschnos, the Shawanese chief having gone to a council at Sir W. Johnson's
  - Advertisement for recruits, July 2, 1756; 157; 2p.; Schlösser, Johannes
    In German and English
  - Advertisement for recruits, July 2, 1756; 159; 1p.; Schlösser, Johannes
    Original of No. 157 in English and German
  - to William Parsons, July 3, 1756; 161; 2p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Re: Lt. Schlosser and about the Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 3, 1756; 165; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Re: to preceding (no. 161), and giving substance of B. Franklin's letter of June 28th
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 4, 1756; 335; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Requesting to retain Indians until Commissioners appoint other plans
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 4, 1756; 171; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Re: Indians
  - to William Parsons, July 4, 1756; 173; 2p.; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760
    Re: outrages of Indians
  - to William Parsons, July 6, 1756; 175; 1p.; Orndt, Jacob
    Re: the murder of four men by the Indians; and about blankets
  - To William Parsons, July 7, 1756; 177; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Acquainting him of arrival of Indians and of his having sent express to the Governor
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 8, 1756; 179; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Thanking him for preceding intelligence
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 8, 1756; 181; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Requesting him to delay the Indians for the Governor's answer, and not to supply powder and shot
  - to William Parsons, July 8, 1756; 183; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Acknowledging preceding. Stating that 4 Indians wish to return home requesting a guard for them and desiring to know whether he shall supply powder and shot
  - to William Parsons, July 9, 1756; 187; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    In reply to preceding
  - to William Parsons, July 9, 1756; 189; 1p.; Horsfield, Timothy, 1708-1773
    Referring to Capt. Inslee
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 9, 1756; 193; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Regretting that the Indians could not go to him; desiring them to be supplied with provisions and ammunition, and to send them away well satisfied
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 9, 1766; 337; 1p.; Morris, Robert Hunter, 1713-1764
    Desiring acknowledgements to Mr. Spangenberg for his trouble in Indian Affairs
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 9, 1756; 191; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Suggesting giving a small quantity of ammunition to the Indians
  - to Timothy Horsfield, July 9, 1756; 195; 1p.; Parsons, William, 1701-1757
    Suggesting giving a small quantity of ammunition to the Indians (original of no. 191)